Guide to the George Eliot and George Henry Lewes Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Section IX. George Eliot. SPECIAL FILES
  - 6. Poems written to or sent to GE
    - Anonymous: a. (Box 63)
    - 1. O painter, match an English, 1873 (Box 63)
    - bloom... (Box 63)
    - 2. Why should I strive to express it?..., 1874 (Box 63)
    - 3. And Love?-thine heart imagined...1875 (Box 63)
    - 4. O when through all the crowd..., 1876 (Box 63)
    - 5. And all is over..., 1877 (Box 63)
    - b. Her eyes were like two quiet stars..., 1854 (Box 63)
    - c. T. George Eliot, signed A. E. I. (Box 63)
    - d. Written in North Wales. (Box 63)
    - e. To the Author of George Eliot's Gospel., 1874 (Box 63)
    - f. To the Writer of "How we reward research"!, 1879 (Box 63)
    - g. [Poem in German] "Noch gläntze im warmenden Sonnenlicht..." (Box 63)
    - h. [Poem in German] "Welch' tiefer Ton dringt an das Ohr?" (Box 63)
    - i. "Paraphrase on a part of the conclusion of The Mill on the Floss". (Box 63)
    - j. Sigrutz, Karl. "The Spanish Gipsey by George Elliot". (Box 63)
    - k. Stanzas from J. R. Lowell's The Present Crisis. (Box 63)
    - l. Brontë, Emily. "Remembrance"., [1879 Dec 18] (Box 63)
      Copy made by Mrs. Hans William Sotheby and sent to GE.
  - 7. Analysis of the water at Witley, 1879 Jun 29 (Box 63)
  - 8. Quotation from Middlemarch used as subject for an essay on the "Examination for First Appointments to the Cavalry and Infantry"., 1874 Aug 15 (Box 63)
  - 9. signed by A.V.A. Water color illustration labelled "Daniel Deronda may he come in?" (Box 63)
    In portfolio in bottom drawer.
  - 10. Braddon, Paul. Eight water color sketches of places connected with GE in folder labelled "Reminiscences of George Eliot". 8 X 10 inches. (Box 63)
  - 11.
    - a. Announcements, programs, etc. for The George Eliot Centennial Conference at the University of Puget Sound, 4 pieces., 1980 Apr 10-12 (Box 63)
    - b. George Eliot. An exhibition at the British Library., 1980 Dec 11-1981 Apr 26 (Box 63)
    - c. Daniel Waley. George Eliot's Blotter. 2 copies. (Box 63)
    - d. Commemorative stamps of George Eliot, Charlotte Brontë, Emily Brontë and Mrs. Gaskell, with an enlarged photograph of the GE stamp. 5 pieces. (Box 63)
    - e. Westminster Abbey. Unveiling and dedication of a memorial to George Eliot. With ticket of admission. 2 pieces., 1980 Jun 21 (Box 63)
    - f. Gordon Haight's speech in Westminster Abbey on 21 June, when a memorial stone to George Eliot was unveiled. Photocopy of the speech printed in the London Review of Books, 17 July - 6 August 1980. (Box 63)
  - 12. "Memorandum Book of Occurences [!] at Nuneaton":, 1810-45 (Box 63)
    transcript of an anonymous journal in the Nuneaton Public Library. 1810-45 (1838-June 1843 lacking). 168 pages. Accompanied by a manuscript list ("from Mrs. Dodds 18 Sept 1950") of the most striking events in the journal.
  - 13. The George Eliot Fellowship., 1953-73 (Box 63)
    Miscellaneous announcements, photographs, clippings, reports, etc.
  - The George Eliot Fellowship Review, No. 1, June 1970- (Box 63)
    Other Finding Aids
    Catalogued separately, See: card catalogue.
- Section X. George Henry Lewes. SPECIAL FILES
  - 1. Articles and stories: printed and proofs
    - a. "Attention." (Box 64)
      Proof of an article printed by the Contemporary Review but never published, nor was it used in the section on attention in Problems of Life and Mind, 3rd series, 1879, p. 184-196.
    - b. "The coming reformation.", 1847 May-Aug (Box 64)
      Four parts signed Vivian [GHL] and published in Douglas Jerrold's Shilling Magazine (May-August 1847) 436-448, 509-519, 35-45, 168-176.
    - c. "The course of modern thought", 1877 Apr (Box 64)
      Fortnightly Review, 21, [317]-327.
    - d. "Dickens in relation to criticism.", 1872 Feb (Box 64)
      Fortnightly Review, 11, [141]-154.
    - e. "The gallant glazier.", 1847 Dec (Box 64)
      Douglas Jerrold's Shilling Magazine, 517-534.
    - f. "Modern French literature.", 1846 Aug 29 (Box 64)
      The Topic, [85]-98.
    - g. "Motor-feeling and the muscular sense.", 1878 Mar 28 (Box 64)
      Second revise proof, printed by Wm. Clowes & Son. Problems of Life and Mind, 1879, 3rd series, Problem III, ch. 7, p. 312-325, uses parts of it, mostly rewritten.
    - h. "A night in a German swamp.", 1847 Feb (Box 64)
      Douglas Jerrold's Shilling Magazine, 161-171.
    - i. "On the dread and dislike of science.", 1878 Jun 1 (Box 64)
      Fortnightly Review, 23, [805]-815.
    - j. "Spiritualism and materialism.", 1876 (Box 64)
      Fortnightly Review, 19, (1 April 1876) [479]-493, 19, (1 May 1876) [707]-719.
    - k. "Trust not your eyes in love", 1848 Jun (Box 64)
    - (followed by) "Men of thought and men of action.", 1848 Jun (Box 64)
      Douglas Jerrold's Shilling Magazine, 499-533.
  - 2. Hamlet. (Box 64)
    Notes for lectures on Hamlet. Passages cut from printed text with manuscript notes interpolated. 46 [i.e. 40] p. in paper cover marked "Hamlet."
  - 3. Syllabus of a course of six lectures on the history of philosophical specu- lation, ancient and modern. Printed syllabus of lectures given at the Liverpool Mechanics Institution in February 1849. (Box 64)
  - 4. Estimates and statements of sales of his books., 1862-99
    - Estimates, 2 pieces., 1862, n.d. (Box 64)
    - Sales by Trübner & Co., 14 pieces., 1877-89 (Box 64)
    - Other sales, 4 pieces., 1875-99 (Box 64)
  - 5. Reviews of The Life and Works of Goethe
    - a. Literary Gazette, 1855 Nov 3 (Box 64)
    - b. Athenaeum, 1855 Nov 10 (Box 64)
    - c. Schöll, Adolf. Weimarer Sontags - Blat. 13 and 27, 1857 Dec (Box 64)
    - d. Siegfried, Heinrich. An G.H. Lewes eine Epistel. Berlin., 1858 (Box 64)
    - e. Duntzer, H. Allgemeiner Zeitung, 1858 Apr 26 (Box 64)
  - 6. Reviews of Problems of Life and Mind:
    a. "Mr. Lewes and Metaphysics" in unidentified periodical. p. 104-137.
    - b. Clifford, W. K. Academy, 1874 Feb 7 (Box 64)
    - c. Ward, James. Academy, 1878 Mar 16 (Box 64)
      p. 237-239.
    - d. Ward, James. Academy, 1878 Apr 20 (Box 64)
      p. 349-350.
    - e. Athenaeum, 1879 Sep 27 (Box 64)
      p. 397-398.
    - f. Spalding, Douglas A. Examiner, 1874 Mar 14 (Box 64)
      p. 261-262.
    - g. Sully, James. Examiner, 1875 Jul 10 (Box 64)
      p. 773-774.
    - h. Sully, James. Examiner, 1875 Jul 17 (Box 64)
      p. 803-804.
    - i. Harrison, Frederic. Fortnightly, (1874) (Box 64)
      16, p. 89-101.
    - j. Courtney, William L. Fortnightly, (1879) (Box 64)
      26, p. 318-328.
    - k. [Proof] Revue Scientifique, (1877) (Box 64)
    - l. Saturday Review, 1875 Sep 4 (Box 64)
      p. 301-302.
    - m. Saturday Review, 1879 Jul 19 (Box 64)
      p. 84-85.
  - 7. Obituary notices
    - a. Harrison, Frederic. Academy, 1878 Dec 7 (Box 64)
      p. 543-544.
    - b. Bartling, Heinrich., 1879 Apr 1 (Box 64)
      Allgemeine Literarische Corres- pondenz, p. 1-2.
    - c. Daily News, 1878 Dec 3 (Box 64)
    - d. Echo, 1878 Dec 2 (Box 64)
    - e. Buchanan, Robert. Examiner, 1878 Dec 7 (Box 64)
      p. 1551.
    - f. Sully, James. New Quarterly Magazine, p. 356-376., 1879 Oct (Box 64)
    - g. Delboeuf, M. J. Revue Scientifique, p. 730-733., 1879 Feb 1 (Box 64)
    - h. The Times, 1878 Dec 3 (Box 64)
    - i. Unidentified. 2 items. (Box 64)
  - 8. George Henry Lewes Studentship, University of Cambridge, founded by George Eliot in 1879.
    a. Letters, etc., relating to the founding of the studentship:
    - 1. Balfour, Francis Maitland, 1851-1882. ALS to Sir Michael Forster, 7 p., [1879] (Box 64)
    - 2. Dyer, William T. Thistleton. Memorandum, 11 p., [1879] (Box 64)
    - 3. Eliot, George. Draft of a plan for the studentship. 3 p., [1879] (Box 64)
    - 4. Forster, Sir Michael, 1836- 1907. 3 ALS to GE, with 2 drafts of plans. May 21, 26, and Jun 10. 2, 4, 4, 6, 9 p., [1879] May-Jun (Box 64)
    - 5. Huxley, Thomas Henry Comments on a proposal for the studentship. 2 p. (Box 64)
    - 6. Paget, Sir James, 1814-1899. ALS to GE, 3 p., 1879 May 24 (Box 64)
    - 7. Pye-Smith, Philip H., Memorandum, 7 p., 1879 May 8 (Box 64)
    - 8. Sidgwick, Henry, 5 ALS to GE. March 2, 4, 12, May 8, 16. 8, 2, 4, 3, 4 p., 1879 Mar-May (Box 64)
    - 9. Sidgwick, Henry. ALS to Sir Michael Forster., [1879] Apr 10 (Box 64)
    - 10. Warren, Charles Harris, 2 ALS to GE. 4, 3 p., 1879 Jul 1 (Box 64)
    - 11. Printed "Extract from the Conditions under which is con- tituted a Studentship of Physiology founded in Memory of George Henry Lewes." 2 p., 1879 Jul 26 (Box 64)
    - 12. Printed "Trust Deed of the "'George Henry Lewes' Studentship." 4 p. 2 copies. (Box 64)
    - 13. Roy, Charles Smart. (the first GHL Student) 2 ALS to GE 12, 4 p., 1879 Nov 17, 1880 Aug 13 (Box 64)
    - b. Letters from applicants for the Studentship:, 1879 Sep (Box 64)
      1. A., the Rev. M. 2. Allen, Frank J. 3. Anderson, L. 4. Bailey, T. R. 5. Bellhouse, F. W. 6. Cameron, W. J. 7. Combs, Annie L. 8. Cooper, Henry Charles Evans 9. Draper, John B., with copies of 3 testimonials
      10. Emmett, R. B. 11. Field, John 12. Harris, D. P. 13. Heath, Alice 14. Huson - More, J. 15. Kempe, C. P. 16. Kent, W. Saville, with printed testimonials 17. Logan, J. R. 18. Mead, George B. 19. Newman, James H.
      20. North, W. 21. Osborn, Ada E. 22. Payne, Georgianna 23. Plummer, H. G. 24. Radford, William 25. Smith, W. F. 26. Waters, W. H. 27. Wheatley, Arthur 28. Younge, George Harrison
  - With 2 newspaper cuttings inviting applications, 1924, 1928
    - c. Correspondence between Ernest Carrington Ouvry and the University of Cambridge relating to the GHL Studentship., 1947-48 (Box 64)
      11 items, including one leaf of notes by Mrs. Ouvry, a list of some of the early Students, and a printed announcement of the vacant Studentship on 1 October 1946.
    - d. Photographs and drawings of GHL.
      - 1. Sketch by Anna Gliddon. Photocopy of the original in the National Portrait Gallery. No. 1373., 1840 (Box 64)
      - 2. Sketch of Agnes Jervis Lewes, George Henry Lewes, and Thornton Leigh Hunt, about 1844. Photocopy of a pencil sketch by W. M. Thackeray in the National Portrait Gallery., c. 1844 (Box 64)
      - 3. Sketch by Rudolf Lehman, dated. Photocopy of the original in the Nuneaton Public Library., 1867 Jun 20 (Box 64)
      - 4. Photograph by Elliott & Fry. (Box 64)
      - 5. Photograph by Mayall. (Box 64)
  - 9. Articles about Lewes
    - a. Noble, D. George Henry Lewes, George Eliot and the Physiological Society. Removed from The Journal of Physiology, December 1976, vol. 263, no. 1, p. 45P-54P., 1976 Dec (Box 64)
- Section XI. Films of Manuscripts
  Microfilms of manuscripts owned by other libraries or individuals formerly held in this collection were discarded by curatorial request April 1997.